<!--
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Chief-Engineer <119664036+Chief-Engineer@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Piras314 <p1r4s@proton.me>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 Aiden <28298836+Aidenkrz@users.noreply.github.com>

SPDX-License-Identifier: AGPL-3.0-or-later
-->

<Document>
  # Roleplay Rule 6 - Antagonism

  Antagonists exist to create conflict, tension, and story. Their role is to meaningfully influence the shift, not simply to remove players from the round.

  Antagonists are expected to engage with their role and pursue a coherent in-character direction. Objectives are guidance, not rigid requirements. An antagonist may ignore or reinterpret their objectives if they have a more interesting or consistent in-character plan. Antagonistic actions that would typically result in removal from the round on other servers may instead result in severe in-character consequences here, such as permanent incarceration or execution. The expectation is that extreme actions are resolved through roleplay whenever possible. However, actions taken without in-character grounding, purely to disrupt the round, or intended to target players out-of-character remain administrative issues.

  ## Precedents
  - Objectives are suggestions, and antagonists are free to ignore them if they have a preferred or more interesting idea for their course of action.
  - Actions as an antagonist do not have to be nefarious or evil, but should make an effort to influence the story and meaningfully impact the shift. Explicitly friendly antagonistic play or siding outright with the crew is discourged – players should have good in-character reasoning behind the decision or an antagonistic goal in mind by doing it.
  - Roleplay rule 11 applies to the actions of antagonists – extremely repetitive antagonistic actions repeated over the long term may draw an administrative request to tone it down or try something new, if most of the people on the server can immediately guess what you’re going to do when made an antagonist, it might be time to come up with a new plan.

  ## Important information regarding antag labels.
  - Traitors and Changelings may team despite being solo antagonists, but risk being a target themselves or double crossed for their biomass or TC.
  - Heretics do not team, they are explicitly solo antagonists, heretics have conflicting ideologies. This puts them at odds with each other. The stronger god wins.
  - Bingles are only interested in feeding the hole. You must feed the hole.
  - The Abductor should not make exxtreme attempts to steal things. They are generally only interested in research. Some trinkets are cool to collect but what use are these normal items?
  - The Thief antagonist should only deliberately kill in self-defense, while protecting their stash, or after proper
  escalation.

  # Restricted Antag Death and Destruction

  Some antagonist roles are restricted in how freely they may cause death or large-scale destruction. These restrictions are not meant to eliminate conflict, but to preserve pacing, escalation, and meaningful consequences.

  ## With Objectives

  Objectives define what an antagonist may directly pursue without needing proportional escalation and suffering perma-brigging. Actions taken specifically to complete an objective do not need to be proportionate. Destruction or killing used indirectly to support an objective must be explainable through events that occurred during the shift. If questioned, the antagonist must be able to clearly explain what led to their decision based on in-character developments. If a crew member or department directly interferes with an objective, this constitutes sufficient in-character justification for escalation.

  Severe actions taken to complete objectives may result in severe in-character consequences.

  ## Without Objectives

  When acting outside of direct objectives, restricted antagonists operate under relaxed escalation standards compared to normal crew. They may escalate sooner, escalate lethally with less buildup, and rely on antagonistic motivations. Minor social slights, exclusion, hostility, or paranoia may serve as justification — provided the antagonist can explain their reasoning in-character. However, minor conflict should not automatically result in permanent round removal unless escalation would otherwise justify it. Even under relaxed standards, actions must still be narratively grounded.

  Antagonists are not required to provide mercy or medical care to their victims. (Though, it is encouraged :3)

  ## Mass Sabotage

  Certain large-scale destructive acts are inherently indiscriminate and cannot reasonably follow proportional escalation. These actions are permitted, even for restricted antagonists, provided they are not used to intentionally maximize personal body count beyond the sabotage itself.

  Examples include plasma flooding, supermatter delamination, or catastrophic station-wide spacing. These actions may cause widespread death.

  The antag should not take additional targeted actions specifically to increase casualties beyond what their sabotage would naturally cause (if it is their goal). 
  Mass sabotage, murder, round removal, and other similar actions taken outside of objectives may result in extreme in-character consequences, including permanent incarceration (spanning over rounds) or execution.
  
  # Is this antagonist role restricted in how it can deliver death and destruction?
  This table covers which antagonists must abide by restrictions in how they deliver death and destruction to the station under RPR 6, as well as any partial or grey-area exemptions.

  <Table Columns="2">
    <ColorBox>
      <Box>
        Antagonist
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box>
        Restriction exempt?
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Traitor
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        No.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Changeling
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        No.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Malfunctioning AI
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Yes.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Nuclear Operative
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Yes.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Wizard
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Yes.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Cosmic Cult/Revolutionary
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        In general no, conversion should take priority, however if the situation is dire you are allowed to kill as many as required to accomplish your goals.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Revenant
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Yes.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Blob
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Yes.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Abductor
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        No.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Space Ninja
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        No.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Pirate
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        No.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Heretic
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Yes, however it should only occur after ascension.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Bingle
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Yes.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Devil
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        No.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Paradox Clone
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        No.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        Thief
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>
    <ColorBox>
      <Box HorizontalAlignment="Left" VerticalAlignment="Stretch" Margin="2">
        No.
      </Box>
    </ColorBox>

  </Table>
</Document>
