<!--
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Aiden <aiden@djkraz.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Chief-Engineer <119664036+Chief-Engineer@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 strO0pwafel <153459934+strO0pwafel@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 Aiden <28298836+Aidenkrz@users.noreply.github.com>

SPDX-License-Identifier: AGPL-3.0-or-later
-->

<Document>
  # Roleplay Rule 3 - Chain of command and security are important.

  The Chain of Command and Security exist to provide structure to the station. If you are Command or Security, you're expected to put in the effort and do your job as a departmental leader.

  If you're not in the Chain of Command, your department head is your boss and they can fire you. They may demote, reassign, or terminate crew members for in-character reasons. Security may detain, search, fine, or arrest crew members based on their in-character judgment of a situation. These decisions do not need to be fair, correct, or morally justified — they may be harsh, biased, mistaken, or even corrupt — provided they are grounded in coherent roleplay and not driven by out-of-character intent.

  Forgery, favoritism, wrongful arrest, or abuse of power are all valid roleplay actions if they are meaningfully portrayed and contribute to the round’s story. However, actions taken purely to grief, target a player out-of-character, or shut down roleplay are not permitted.
  Abuse of power invites in-character consequences, including resistance, exposure, demotion, mutiny, or retaliation.

  *These actions are not punishments for the player — they are in-character consequences and are expected*

  ## Precedents
  
  - The internal chain of command for security is: Head of Security > Warden > Detective > Officers > Cadets
  - Security personnel are generally expected to follow the orders of their superiors. However, orders may be interpreted, challenged, ignored, or even deliberately undermined if supported by coherent in-character reasoning. Internal conflict within Security is valid roleplay.
  - Severe punishments such as permanent incarceration or execution should involve higher authority when reasonably possible. Bypassing a superior for dramatic, corrupt, or urgent reasons is permitted if it is meaningfully roleplayed and not done to avoid consequences.
</Document>
