<!--
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Chief-Engineer <119664036+Chief-Engineer@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 Aiden <28298836+Aidenkrz@users.noreply.github.com>

SPDX-License-Identifier: AGPL-3.0-or-later
-->

<Document>
  # Roleplay Rule 1 - Basic Roleplay Standards

  ## Stay In Character
  Keep IC out of OOC, and OOC out of IC. Your words and actions ingame should be distinguishable as an in-universe character, and not as a person playing a game. Playstyles that disregard all opportunities for engagement and roleplay can be met with administrative action. There is an exception for OOC in IC where terms like 'clickdrag X to Y, or look for the tab' is used to help a player.

  ## Escalation
  Violence may be initiated without prior warning if it is grounded in coherent character motivation. Premeditated or surprise attacks (for example, stalking, leaving messages, building tension, or planning a targeted killing) are permitted, even if they appear sudden to others, provided they are part of an intentional roleplay arc and not arbitrary disruption. (Though we permit more freedom in regards to escalation and self-antagonism, we still expect players to have some level of IC justification for their actions and to not just randomly attack people without reason.)
  If you are attacked, you may defend yourself — including with lethal force. Self-defense is permitted when proportionate to the threat. The level of force used must somewhat reasonably reflect the danger presented. Players who initiate conflict without legitimate IC justification, such as theft or aggression without an argument, may not claim lethal self-defense if reasonable or excessive force is used against them in response. 
  Escalation used as a shortcut to only create chaos or bypass roleplay expectations is not permitted. 
  
  ### Precedents
  - References to the current round, even if vague, are still considered being IC in OOC.
  - Players are free to fight, escalate conflicts, and even kill, provided there is meaningful in-character reasoning and roleplay effort behind those actions. Random or contextless violence with no attempt at roleplay may be treated as disruptive.
  - You may play morally questionable or unstable characters. However, mass violence or extreme behavior must involve genuine roleplay intent rather than serving as a substitute for interaction.
  - Make a reasonable effort for your character name to fit within a futuristic space setting. Real-world names are allowed. Names that are intentionally unreadable, disruptive, or explicitly OOC/mechanic-referencing may be disallowed.


</Document>
