<!--
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Aiden <aiden@djkraz.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Chief-Engineer <119664036+Chief-Engineer@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 strO0pwafel <153459934+strO0pwafel@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 Aiden <28298836+Aidenkrz@users.noreply.github.com>

SPDX-License-Identifier: AGPL-3.0-or-later
-->

<Document>
  # Roleplay Rule 4 - Command Responsibility and Mindshield Expectations

  ## Command and Vital Roles
  Heads of Staff and other important roles (such as the Station AI, NTR, BSO, etc.) are expected to perform the minimum of the core responsibilities of their department to a reasonable standard. These roles carry significant authority and influence over the round.

  Command members may demote staff for in-character reasons. Security may perform arrests based on in-character suspicion or judgment. These actions do not need to be fair or optimal, but they must be grounded in coherent roleplay. 

  Due to the nature of this server, both Command and Security are permitted broad discretion in how they exercise authority. They may act acrimoniously, unfairly, or abusively as part of roleplay, provided their actions are supported by meaningful in-character reasoning and are not purely disruptive.
  The Chain of Command and Security exist to provide structure to the station. If you are Command or Security, you're expected to put in the effort and do your job as a departmental leader.
  If you're not in the Chain of Command, your department head is your boss and they can fire you. They may demote, reassign, or terminate crew members for in-character reasons. Security may detain, search, fine, or arrest crew members based on their in-character judgment of a situation. These decisions do not need to be fair, correct, or morally justified — they may be harsh, biased, mistaken, or even corrupt — provided they are grounded in coherent roleplay and not driven by out-of-character intent.

  Forgery, favoritism, wrongful arrest, or abuse of power are all valid roleplay actions if they are meaningfully portrayed and contribute to the round’s story. However, actions taken purely to grief, target a player out-of-character, or shut down roleplay are not permitted.
  These actions invite in-character consequences, including resistance, exposure, demotion, mutiny, or retaliation.
  [bold]These actions are not punishments for the player — they are in-character consequences and are expected[/bold]

  Things to keep in mind:
  - The internal chain of command for security is: Head of Security > Warden > Detective > Officers > Cadets
  - Security personnel are generally expected to follow the orders of their superiors. However, orders may be interpreted, challenged, ignored, or even deliberately undermined if supported by coherent in-character reasoning. Internal conflict within Security is valid roleplay.
  - Severe punishments such as permanent incarceration or execution should involve higher authority when reasonably possible. Bypassing a superior for dramatic, corrupt, or urgent reasons is permitted if it is meaningfully roleplayed and not done to avoid consequences.

  ## Nanotrasen Representative Rules
  - You are to represent NT, send reports back to them on the stations' situation, inform the heads of anything CentCom orders them to do. Stay on task and avoid doing anything else apart from this.
  - You are to also guide the Station Heads, along with the Blueshield if needed. If you can't provide an answer, try ahelping for one.
  - Do not abuse your extra access for malicious reasons. Only use it if you must.
  - Use common sense and remember that you are also held up to a high standard of play. Failure to do so will lead to a roleban from command or gameban from the server entirely.

  ## Blueshield Officer Rules
  - You are to protect the Station Heads and Central Command VIPs from danger. You are not a Security Officer with extra access, so do not abandon your duties.
  - You are held up to a higher standard of play as command and Security. Take your job seriously, and do it right.
  - You answer to the Central Command only. Follow directives to your best ability.
  - Do not abuse your role, and use common sense. If you have questions or concerns, ahelp them for the Admins to answer or try asking in the Discord. Failure to do so can lead to a roleban from command or gameban.
  - Do not make yourself Captain or any other command job. If you want to be Captain, instead choose that role while in the lobby.

  [bold]A reasonable effort should be made to enter cryosleep when leaving to free the role slot.[/bold]

  ## Mindshielded Personnel
  [bold]Mindshield implants are a lore-enforced behavioral safeguard. Characters who are mindshielded are considered mentally stabilized and resistant to violent, rogue, or extremist impulses.[/bold]

  Mindshielded individuals may not engage in random, purposeless destruction, murder, or raider-style behavior without clear and defensible in-character reasoning.
  This does not mean mindshielded characters must be passive. Characters may also not intentionally remove or sabotage their implant for the purpose of enabling otherwise prohibited violent or destructive behavior.
  They may:
  - Use force in self-defense
  - Use force in defense of others
  - Engage in morally questionable or controversial actions if supported by coherent reasoning
  
  However, actions that resemble indiscriminate killing, chaotic destruction, or violence without grounded motive are considered a violation of the server’s internal logic — similar in principle to a silicon intentionally violating its laws. Put simply, you may escalate as far as you can roleplay and justify but mindshielded characters cannot “go rogue” without cause.
  Mindshielded characters may not intentionally remove or sabotage their implant for the purpose of enabling otherwise prohibited violent or destructive behavior. If a character becomes unmindshielded, and the player intends to act violently as a result, that intent must be roleplayed as emerging from the loss of stabilization. Sudden, consequence-free behavioral shifts without roleplay justification may be treated as rule violations.
  Attempting to circumvent this standard through technicalities, implant removal, or bad-faith interpretation may result in role bans, including permanent bans from Command or Security.

</Document>
