<!--
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Chief-Engineer <119664036+Chief-Engineer@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 Aiden <28298836+Aidenkrz@users.noreply.github.com>

SPDX-License-Identifier: AGPL-3.0-or-later
-->

<Document>
  # Core Rule 5 - Command Responsibility and Mindshield Expectations

  ## Command and Vital Roles
  Heads of Staff and other vital leadership roles are expected to perform the minimum of the core responsibilities of their department to a reasonable standard. These roles carry significant authority and influence over the round.

  Command members may demote staff for in-character reasons. Security may perform arrests based on in-character suspicion or judgment. These actions do not need to be fair or optimal, but they must be grounded in coherent roleplay. 

  Due to the nature of this server, both Command and Security are permitted broad discretion in how they exercise authority. They may act acrimoniously, unfairly, or abusively as part of roleplay, provided their actions are supported by meaningful in-character reasoning and are not purely disruptive.

  A reasonable effort should be made to enter cryosleep when leaving to free the role slot.

  ## Mindshielded Personnel
  *Mindshield implants are a lore-enforced behavioral safeguard. Characters who are mindshielded are considered mentally stabilized and resistant to violent, rogue, or extremist impulses.*

  Mindshielded individuals may not engage in random, purposeless destruction, murder, or raider-style behavior without clear and defensible in-character reasoning.
  This does not mean mindshielded characters must be passive. Characters may also not intentionally remove or sabotage their implant for the purpose of enabling otherwise prohibited violent or destructive behavior.
  They may:
    - Use force in self-defense
    - Use force in defense of others
    - Engage in morally questionable or controversial actions if supported by coherent reasoning
  
  However, actions that resemble indiscriminate killing, chaotic destruction, or violence without grounded motive are considered a violation of the server’s internal logic — similar in principle to a silicon intentionally violating its laws. Put simply, you may escalate as far as you can roleplay and justify but mindshielded characters cannot “go rogue” without cause.
  Mindshielded characters may not intentionally remove or sabotage their implant for the purpose of enabling otherwise prohibited violent or destructive behavior. If a character becomes unmindshielded, and the player intends to act violently as a result, that intent must be roleplayed as emerging from the loss of stabilization. Sudden, consequence-free behavioral shifts without roleplay justification may be treated as rule violations.
  Attempting to circumvent this standard through technicalities, implant removal, or bad-faith interpretation may result in role bans, including permanent bans from Command or Security.


</Document>
