<!--
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Chief-Engineer <119664036+Chief-Engineer@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 Aiden <28298836+Aidenkrz@users.noreply.github.com>

SPDX-License-Identifier: AGPL-3.0-or-later
-->

<Document>
  # Core Rule 4 - Antagonists and Escalation Freedom

  With the exception of metagaming, exploit abuse, ERP, OOC/IC violations, or spawn-camping arrivals, lone antagonists are largely free to pursue their objectives in any manner they choose. Team antagonists operate under the same freedom as lone antagonists but must not intentionally undermine their team’s objectives through sabotage, refusal to participate, or bad-faith inaction.

  This freedom is conditional on effort and roleplay. Escalation is permitted — including extreme escalation — when supported by meaningful in-character reasoning and interaction.

  Crewmembers are permitted to investigate, question, or monitor others if they develop reasonable in-character suspicion. You do not need to be Security to be cautious or investigative. However, pre-emptive detainment, lethal force, or murder without sufficient in-character cause may be treated as disruptive. Suspicion should arise from in-round behavior, not assumptions based on role likelihood, player patterns, or OOC knowledge.

  Once conflict is remotely justified, crewmembers may respond as they see fit, understanding that their actions remain subject to in-character consequences such as Space Law. Acting like an antagonist in action or appearance may result in being treated as one in-character.

  ## Antagonist Directive Priorities
  - In situations where you wind up with multiple simultaneous antagonist assignments (i.e. a Revolutionary and a Traitor), your team goals, objectives, and directives should take precedence. Furthermore, if someone had to go out of their way to convert you to their team, their goals, objectives, and directives become the priority. Refer to the following flowchart:
  - Blob/Zombie -> Brainwash/Construct orders/Silicon Laws -> Cult/Heretic -> Revs -> Wizard Apprentice/Abductor Teams/Niche antags -> Nuke Ops -> Traitors

</Document>
