<!--
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Aiden <aiden@djkraz.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Chief-Engineer <119664036+Chief-Engineer@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Moomoobeef <62638182+Moomoobeef@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Piras314 <92357316+Piras314@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 basic pack <159909786+packmore@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 Aiden <28298836+Aidenkrz@users.noreply.github.com>

SPDX-License-Identifier: AGPL-3.0-or-later
-->

<Document>
  # Roleplay Rules
  These rules only apply during a round. A round ends only when the round summary has appeared. All of these rules apply fully until the moment that the round summary appears, even while the arrivals shuttle is in transit.
  Roleplay rules do not apply to ghosts/spectators/observers while they are ghosts/spectators/observers. Dead chat is considered to be an in-game out of character chat channel.
  See the list of [textlink="Role Types" link="RoleTypes"] for more information about the different types of roles.

  ## Character Rules
  These rules apply to all characters.
  - [textlink="1. Try to use proper escalation" link="WCRuleR1"]
  - [textlink="2. Follow New Life Rule (NLR)" link="WCRuleR2"]
  - [textlink="3. No Extreme Metagaming" link="WCRuleR3"]
  - [textlink="4. Chain of Command" link="WCRuleR4"]
  - [textlink="5. Self-Antagonism and Antagonist Rules" link="WCRuleR5"]
  - [textlink="6. Don't overdo criminal punishments" link="WCRuleR6"]

  ## Silicon Rules
  You are only silicon if the game clearly and explicitly tells you that you are a silicon. For players who are silicons, these Silicon Rules override all roleplay rules if there is any conflict. Silicon Rules do not override core rules.
  - [textlink="1. Your silicon laws are rules" link="RuleS1"]
  - [textlink="2. Laws must be prioritized by their order" link="RuleS2"]
  - [textlink="3. Laws can redefine terms used in other laws" link="RuleS3"]
  - [textlink="4. You cannot request or allow a law change" link="RuleS4"]
  - [textlink="5. You are a free agent if you have no laws" link="RuleS5"]
  - [textlink="6. You are not required to follow orders which are extremely unreasonable" link="RuleS6"]
  - [textlink="7. You must remain consistent with your interpretation of laws" link="RuleS7"]
  - [textlink="8. Your HUD determines who is crew" link="RuleS8"]
  - [textlink="9. Harm refers to physical harm, prioritized by immediacy and likelihood" link="RuleS9"]
  - [textlink="10. You may determine how you resolve conflicts between orders" link="RuleS10"]

</Document>
